本字幕由 avplayer.org 社区出品
gentleman please welcome Charles Torre
excellent. thanks for showing up
it's great to able to do goingnative again.
last year was awesome, wonderful to see all you people, all you programmers in the audience
there is people on-line
thanks to the channel9 team for streaming this live,
very appreciate that. so you can ask questions on-line.
But we gona take questions from people on this rooms priority you came.
That's excellent.
We have a great 3 days for you.
today we gona say pretty much iso for day1 and day2.
mainly focus on standard c++.
day3 we gonna kind of  some windows
some more vc++.
I'd like to introduce our key note speaker.
so we want to have Bjarne Stroupstrup to appear.
the creator of c++
he's gonna teach us a little bit about the essences.
thanks for come-ing !
------
OK, here. welcome, seams the mic working.
so, in the next couple of days, you are going to hear a lot about the latest and greatest in c++.
you are going to hear a lot about advanced tech and new features.
and I decide that in the keynote, I couldn't go too much into that.
so I'm going to try to do the opposite.
I'm going to try and focus on what is the essence of c++ .
what is it that's been constant over the decades.
and basically that is it what kept c++ alive and kicking.
of course I cann't quite insist showing some new and nice stuff
so the last 15min or so will be about something from c++14.
but basically I'll talk about aims and constraints , and the development first.
I'm trying to explain c++ in four slides.
and then going to some details of resource management, oop , ge, what challenge ahead.
so, basically, that is what we want , out of a programming language that is aim among things for system programming.
We want type safety.
That will be ideal, we can't be perfect about that
with the need to deal close to the hardware. and with the C inheritance .
but it's an idea , it's something we aim to improve.
We want resource safety.
that is not just memory.
so i'm going to argue that we we really don't want to leak anything.
and "things" can be, things like locks and file handles, not just memory.
I'm going to talk about performance
because , well,
that is important.
if it isn't important to you , that might be better language for you to do.
predictability is very important for very large component of the c++ world.
er, dealing with hardware, dealing with things that has to be happen quickly or reliable or repeatedly .
and we can languages that can be taught.
we want something that is no more complex than the needs to be for the tasks is doing.
and of course we want to be able to read what we are doing.
you can writ unreadable code in any language of course.
but, we want to be able to write some thing on a good day
that people say, "wow, this is realy nice and clean an clear."
these are the aims we much better added today than we were 20 years ago
and will be actually much better next year when we get c++14
and , we want...
the primary concerns of mine, is system programming, embedded systems, resource constrain systems, and large systems.
that is ... err...
so, strictly, the domain of high qualified professional programmers.
and it may very well means that if you have a tool for that, it's good for a lot of other things.
that was one of my surprises early on was that
.. so many systems has a clue to it
where what I mostly interest in is essential
and then c++ is so general, that it well do the rest also.
so, c++ is expert friendly, definitely. and, the problem is , that's not enough.
if it is only expert friendly,  if it just expert friendly, that's nothing for narcosis.
we must involve the language into somthing that is a bit more friendly to narcosis
without give in an inch of / bytes and cycle for the experts, what they really needs is bytes an cycles.
so part of this is my answer to what is c++.
I .. I  .., I have my ideas that's not necessary the same as anybody else is.
there are probably a big border than what you hear in most places
that is I try to see the whole elephant
and I find that
in forums on the web and conferences as such
people play Blind Men and the Elephant
and they are absolutely certain that their part of the elephant is the whole beast.
there are wrong.
so this is my summery of c++
if you have to do in one slide.
its a language that provides light weight abstraction facilities
and its key strength scenario is where you build software infrastructure
and where you have resource constraint applications.
it's not the elephant
it's light weight
it's the abstraction you can build
that is anybody can build a really slow
big abstraction.
but, building a point or coordinate or complex number
that you can afford in competition language that is building facilities like that, is hard.
and that's what c++'s strength is.
c++ is developed
comes from two of the main lines of development of programming language.
the lower line here
were basically exploit the hardware
start with assembler
went though BCPL
and C
and C++ gets a lot of its low level stuff from C.
you can see people there
, that's of course Dennis Ritchie
that's David Wheeler
my thesis advisor
and one of the ten people claim to written the first compiler
he can also claim to have written the first program even running on a store program computer.
so this is .. a .. good thing
good
long tradition exploit the hardware maximally.
on the other hand
the biggest improvement
in programming languages ever
was done by Backus' team at IBM.
when they decide to improve productivity of programmers
by letting programmers write in a language that fit for humans
instead of those load&store hardware close stuff.
so they got Fortran
and you could get
... err ...
programs written in exactly your own language
provide you are certain kind of engineer
or certain kind of scientist.
so that's how we go Fortran.
and as soon as this idea was heard
everybody wanted their language
from their particular domain.
so the business people got Cobol
where you can say business like things
copy files, write to tap and things like that.
err ....
and
very soon , there was a couple of hundreds of languages.
and it is a terrible mess.
because, every language that was good at one thing
you speak one language of one subset of the computing community.
and, so the brilliant ideal here
from Kristen Nygaard
was to generalize these thing
ok
if you have a concept
if you have an idea
in your head
on you blackboard
or what ever
you should be able to put it into a language in general.
so instead of building language around special purpose concept
you provide the facility for building new things.
they called it classes, and class hierarchies
here comes the line of general purpose abstraction from the hardware
and I brow that
and got the initial c++.
we've been developing that ever since
and that's been a lot of development in the world of course
but I'm talking about this line here.
so
what we need, is to be able to do things really well close to the hardware
as well as anybody
and
provide general purpose abstraction so that we can actually get the concepts we need in our program as opposed to always talk about bits and bytes.
so, c++ is of course not perfect
anybody who will claims to have a prefect language
is either sale man
or fool
or both
c++ doesn't actually aim to do everything for everybody.
there are things that are less interesting and things that
you just don't need
say, the efficiency
close to hardware things
or you don't need the abstraction.
there are alternatives
we are not trying to be every thing for everybody.
you has a solid fundamental model
despite what you might have heard, or what your professors might have told you in class.
that quite solid model for what c++ is not try to conventional about that
but
basically has C's model of the hardware
and has facilities for principle to add new concept to a program.
and then this has been refined for 30+ years
that is it works
this also means, that it has a lot of "what's"
it also means we know the "what's".
people very often shows something new
because, well, they haven't learn it's weakness yet
so it looks perfect.
we know the problems of c++
that's partly an advantage
long term stability is a feature.
that is in the despoil compatibility stuff and crud
you find that
it is really nice that, my programs from ten years ago still runs.
it is really nice because it's sort of assures that our program will run in ten years again.
we trying not to break old code
and performance we want to be a match for everything in usually we are.
and this leads to a set of interesting applications for instance that are very widely used.
it actually
what c++ offers cleanly pays off for somebody
otherwise they wouldn't be using it.
so i'm going to go into this a little bit detail.
i'm going to try and get c++ down to just four slides.
and the rest is details.
if you understand int and vector
you understand c++
and there are a lot of details.
but don't get lost in them
that's the point.
btw
I've just written another book
it's very thin
180 pages of stuff plus an index
which claims to present all of c++
at certain level of detail.
so, if you actually are an inexperienced programmer
here is where you can get an idea of c++.
so, that's the end of the advertising.  for now.
er
so
what do we do
the c++ first of all,
we have to map things to hardware
the hardware is where programs run.
they don't run in mathematical abstractions. the run on hardware.
and basically the primitives operation are instructions of the machine.
we have value types (many of them) map directly to machine instructions, some don't. but they are simple. they are values.
if you understand integer , you understand about anything that is a values
you can copy an integer, you can do things to it.
the other kinds are handles
they have handle to control access to values.
so, here for instance
we have a vector that keeps track of how many elements that are
and give you a subscript operation and copy operation and things like that to manipulate the value.
and there is a lot of things like that
but those are two fundamental building blocks we've got
and we compose them by simple concatenation.
that's what happens to an array, you put objects next to each other.
and classes/structs where you put them next to each other usually considered different dimension.
but basically there is nothing more to it.
there're ways of composing these basic things
and when you look at your code. you can sort of think about what is in the memory and understand it
and when it comes to an primitive operation you can see which primitive operations are done.
then, to get away from this very concrete low level view
we have classes
the most important part of  classes I think acturally is constructors and destructors.
we define ourself a new type
and when we initialize it
with some value
that's called construction
when we're finished, clean up the mess.
if this is a resource handle, this will acquire resources and this will release it.
so, basically there is a clue form about two weak insulate design we've seen in classes long time ago.
a constructor establishes the environment for the members to run in
the destructor reverse its actions.
it's like a pair of pants phrase
because I haven't invent the word constructor and destructor yet.
but, that's where a lot of c++ comes from. right there.
and .. now ..
once we've got classes, eventually we get abstract classes and inheritance.
here's the wey we define a interface that is complete insulate users from the implementation or visa versa.
it has couple of virtual functions that of
pure virtual functions.
there is no data members so it's not a brittle base class
you have to manipulate these things through pointers
and references at least that's what essentially every body does.
and that imply some overhead
and it apply some lifetime management
that can be very messy if you don't think it through.
and you can build these hierarchy base on that.
next, we have parametrized types and classes using templates
that's the essential support for generic programming.
and secondly it allows compile-time computation.
basically you can have a vector that's parametrized by element type
you can and have a sort function that's parametrized by it's container type.
and so we can make a vector of doubles like that, an we can sort some vector with that.
that's the essences of generic programming as represented in c++ and supported
there are some things said and it's not c++
it said it's not everything
some of these things that are really quite fundamental in the design of c++ for good and bad is that no crucial dependence on a garbage collector.
a garbage collector is centralize resources so that's contention for it , in a machine .
I remember the big old time machines
64 processors
real beast
what we do?
63 of them are sit waiting for the garbage collector
c++ is designed not to have this problem
it has other problems in exchange. but this is fundamental issues.
similarly, there is not guarantee type safety.
we did not want it for all constructs
we needed C compatibility
we have history
there are needs to deal with hardware that requires break in the type system
we like to minimize
we like to encapsulated it.
but there was a decision a long time ago that c++ runs on a real machine
it not a mathematical abstraction that it grounds on.
and it no virtual machines
if you wanted to run on a virtual machine
you can
but something has to run on the real machine on the real hardware
for instance the implementation of a virtual machine.
and also there are many domains in which that you can not afford a virtual machine
and you can want to exploit the facilities of the hardware.
if you running in a virtual machine, exploiting a GPU gets rather tricky
if you are on the machine itself , you can go to something that might be type unsafe, that might be an extension, but you can get there.
I have a feel, pictures on these slides, they temped us to do something with c++, so you can wonder what it is.
that, that , there is a distributed computing system with wheels.
there are also things that are not c++ for reasons that are regrettable but they are market realities.
there is no huge standard library
because we don't have a owner
we don't have a sugar dady that can produce free libraries to ensure market share.
we would like to fix that
i'm sure Herb (Herb Sutter) would say something about it
yeah he's got a big screen on this. it's one of his favorite topics.
and, we have no central authorities to approve or reject or help integration of the libraries.
integration of libraries is very difficult.
and we would like to do much better than this.
but for the moment, these are the market realities, this is the way the world have been. for c++ all the time.
so we have no standard GUI library. we have, maybe 25 competing frameworks which is just as bad as none.
awfully , again, it's unfortunate.
we don't have all of these things here standard
they exist
you can pick them up
you can use them today
but they are non-standard. we would like to do better than that.
I don't know if you remember the dragon book
that the knight is slaying dragons on complicity like that.
well, some time the dragon wins.
ok,  going to start on slightly more kicking things. we'll go look at resource management.
basically we have things that we would like to control in system
like memory, the elements of a vector, the characters of a string, the file handles that your operation system provides, threads, locks and things like that.
and basically what we want to do is to have a handle that we used to control access and make it convenient to use these things.
basically , the standard way of using this, is to uses constructor and destructor.
the constructor acquires the resource, here it's memory because it's a vector.
and the destructor, well , gives the memory back again.
so it's very simple
here we have a function
has a vector
it makes a vector
and at the end, when ever we leaves the function, how ever we leave, the destructor cleans up by releasing the memory again.
when ever we leaves the function, how ever we leave it
the destructor cleans up by releasing the memory again.
the basic idea is very very simple
details can be quite heavy depend on the resource, depend on the constraints of the  problems and as such.
but keep that picture in mind. and you can write a lot of good code.
the handle usually is scoped.
as long as the handle is in a scope, and not put on the free store itself , and it's helded by a handle
clean up is automatic and simple
the resource is held for a minimal amount of time
name is scope in which was created.
and basically this is sort of the code here
what the constructor do?
it acquire a resource
set the memory, initialize the memory needed to control things
and possibly does some initialization over what resource has acquired.
and the destructor reverse that
very simple.
so
a resource is anything you acquire and have to release. explicitly or implicitly
that's my definition of resource
and a resource should have a owner
I really dislike stuff that just flat around in the system
and well
people hope some body will take care of them. at some point.
if there is an owner
the owner's job is to make sure the life time is managed, it's initialized up properly and cleaned up properly.
and the ultimate rule for resource is it's scope handle
doesn't have to be scoped, but it's easier if you keep it scoped.
it is also know as Resource Acquisition Is Initialization.
horrible morph. often reduced to RAII.
I can say it's a horrible morph because I invented it and I name it
I should have named it something better
but
well
hand side is relatively easy.
and basically if you failed to acquire your resource
you throw an exception.
it's one of the fundamental reasons that exceptions are in c++.
it is that has to be a way of getting out of a task that you have been ask to do
can't do
like constructor can't construct its object
it has to be able to get out of there
if you don't have exceptions you have to fake them.
em
you try to construct an object, but the object
but the object  are set in a bad state
and you have to test validate
something like that
pretty horrible stuff
and basically
the rules for not leaking becomes
never throw while holding a resource that's not own by a handle
so
if you do something silly
like acquire some memory, and hold an pointer to it
and throw exception, you're are in deep trouble
we'll get back to that.
ok
here is an example
we have a mutex
it's a system resource
and..
sorry
we have something we want to share, which is a shared data here
and we want to controlle it by a mutex.
mutex is an standard system resource, and it it represented in the standard library by the mutex class
and the mutex class is actually a handle to the system resource
and so ...
what ... er ...
system resource...
yeah
just think about that
it is a system resource
we going to a scope
we take a lock on it.
that is the local object that hold the mutex.
use the data
and we go out of there.
we don't care how we go out of there.
now this is of course the overly simplified
we don't ...
we often have more code working in that critical regin just there
so we can goes out of there by
returnning
by falling off the scope
or by throwing an exception
but with all of these cases
the lock guard
will release the resource\
that's the main point.
acquire --  use  -- release
so
here is an example of
what code I found when I look around that I think is pretty awful.
it's not just written by java programmers
but it's just getting more common that it used to be.
there is always people writing code like the screen here
but unfortunately this is an increasingly problem.
so
I ... get a gadget
get it on the free store
I learned  object oriented programming
every thing has to be on the free store
I manipulate it through pointers
so that's what I'm doing.
then I go down
I may throw an exception
and I ...
some one might say why exceptions are bad
because I may leak the gadget. '
No, I'm saying you did something else wrong
because you can get the same problem just from returning.
in other words
i have this gadget here  that i have acquired I have to delete it
and some how that puts major constraint on what I can write in the function.
in particular, I mustn't leave without deleting p
and people then say they want the garbage collector
which you known
I didn't tell you what is inside the gadget
if that's just memory, a garbage collector will help you.
if it's a file handle
a socket
and a lock
err....
the garbage collector will not help you.
so
this code is bad.
if I throw here
I have leak the gadget, and gadget holds a lot of thing.
so, naked pointers are bad.
because they are hard to manage.
so people say, let's use a share pointer.
a share pointer is one of these handles, they hold a  pointer
and when you acquire a pointer, It holds it. and if you goes out of the scope, the share pointer will release the resource
if it io the last one, that holds it
in other words
a share pointer is a form of garbage collection.
If i have a share pointer
I give you a copy, i give you a copy
and the last one of us that gives up the copy , will destroy the object.
that's the idea of share pointer.
but you know
i'm not actually share anything with anybody here
that gadget is mine on mine.
and so
why am i dealing with garbage collection here?
even the shared pointer version of garbage collection
if you people think I misused the word garbage collection
remember that original garbage collection is defined by share pointer, counted pointers.
and because the language calles them self garbage collected, because every thing is a shared pointer.
this is a form of garbage collection.
but , you know, that the use count for the gadget goes from 0 to 1
and eventualy from 1 to 0 , which is what it does
I'm not sharing anything.
there is standard library unique pointer
that would allow me to say just hold on this one
destroy it if i leave this scope
when I leave the scope,  that's all , that's unique pointer. don't share with any body, that's fine.
but, do you know?
why am I dealing with pointers here?
actually the code I would like to become common and ??
is actually like this
I make an gadget
what should the gadget be ?
a gedget should be nice thing. if it hold some thing, it would be an handle to what it holds
if is a file handle in it , the constructor will initialize the file handle and the destructor will close the file again.
if it has a lock, it will do locks unlocks as needed,
if owns a memory, it will acquire memory on construct and release the memory in destructor.
all of those automatic is gadget's job to maintain the gadget's resource. right ?
I mean
i have an abstraction should be proper abstract
these should be no longer a problem.
because the destructor for the gadget, will take care of it.
and some, things are simple.
I really like it when you take some complicated code like that
and improve it
by make it much more simpler.
that's the idea. we want to have simple things simple.
there are things can not do, with just RAII model. there are complicated data structures that require more thought
there are places where you require share pointer etc, etc.
but simple things should be simple.
and this is am example of it.
so, what do we actually use pointers for?
if i'm saying, pointers should not represent ownership.
handles represent ownership
and pointers live inside handler, and are used by them
also, you represent resource inside a handle.
you represent positions.
so that's why we have .... ..
pointers into arrays  like we use indexes.
and we have iterators, all of these god stuff which are pointers in disguise
by and large
represent positions we have to be careful, we can have range checking.
they (pointers) are really good to pass in large amount of data around.
usually in the form of reference or const reference.
that's how we get to say two matries into a add function
for matrices, we pass const references.
pointers in various guises  are really good thing to pass things to others.
people use pointers to pass things out of functions' results
and I'm going to show alternative to that.
so here is the problem
we can get informations, representatives inside functions, we can get informations into functions, but how do we get it out again?
the idea of getting things out of a function
usually if it's a lot of data
or if it is a complicated object
we put it on the free store, and return a pointer to the object we put on the free store
the problem is, we use "new" to get things on free store, so who delete?
is the operation that create the object? or the code that call the object?
neither of those solutions are ideal
neither of those solutions are un-manageable
but a lot of the un-manageable resource management using a lot of pointers. has a root in these problems.
people don't decide who owns what and who cleans what
so things pass to an interface, and disappear
we can try and solve by references. that's even worse.
because I return some reference to something that's on the free store
omebody still has to leak the pointer.
and the obverse question is, what pointer? I don't see any pointer.
A reference looks -- when used -- use like an object. and you have disguise the problem rather that solve it.
we can pass a target object
so instead of adding two matrices and returning a result
we can say add(a,b,c);
it takes a + b and put the result to what ever c points to.
that's a popular way of doing it.
the problem is where it regress towards simply code.
and output parameters is one of sources to complex and confusion.
when I say  plus(a,b,c), what does that mean?
I have to read the documentation.
at least we have const, so that we can tell which one is suppose to be inputs and which one is not.
but if people are not consistent and they just look at the code.
what's what ?
this is source of bugs.
similarly, the code before hand just looks like a becomes b + c
now looks declare some result type c, and then plus a become b become c
that some time it doubles the amount of code you have to write.
I don't like the solution
it works, some time it's the best we can do.
but we are regression
we throwing away few hundred years of progress in notation.
and we can return an object. when we try that, that works nice.
if the object we are returning is an integer, or complex number (: std::complex<>）that's not a problem.
if it is a matrix of a million elements, even a modern process can ... can feel the pain
and so, copies can be expensive, and then we start eventing tricks for returning objects cheaply.
well
that sort of works in the hand of competence programmer in a code base strictly controlled by somebody knows well  doing it works
but in this area here
is where we found a lot of the awful code that, for not solving this problem permanence a million line  code base and become sources of problems.
we can return a handle
don't return the elements of the matrix, don't return pointer to the elements
return the matrix which is the handle
ok, so, how do we do this.
here,
this is what the way we want the code to work.
i want a matrix that takes two .. (BS纠正口误)... plus operation that takes two inputs and produces the result.
I want to do that by making up a local variable
I want to fill it up with the good stuff i want to get out. and I want to return it.
and I write my code like this.
and
this , this works nicely.
n here, "r" is a handle to all the elements
and the return operation is simply
take that point there and give it "res".
and then put a nullptr in its place. that's know as move operation.
even little kids can understand this
look！
here is an object right, I moved it over here.  it not here.
ok. only a computer scientist would make a copy, move the copy over here, and destroy the original.
You actually need a degree to figure that one out.
little kids at about 8 - 6 month can do this.
ok, that does it look like in code？
this is a funny notation, that this one is a move constructor.
a move constructor is called from some thing that we don't need any more.
like the source of a return statement.
and it does exactly this as I said.
here, it copies the representation and zeros out the representation.
it copies because that's what hardware does well for small things like a pointer, or integer.
and the matrix simply is just integer
it may be ... a pointer ...  and it may be a pointer and a couple of dimensions -- its small.
so
we...
this operation here, the move operation is .. is something that is really cheep.
so if you want to move a million elements matrix out of an operation, it cost two DWORD assignment. that that's affordable.
ok
so .. errr.
this leads me to the conclusion that no garbage collection is needed for this simple implicit and efficient resource management
we can do that
and so , we had a set of techniques
fist we store data in containers
and they should reflect the fundamental abstraction in their interface
and they handles lifetime management.
and you handle all resources with resource handle. not just memory
this is important. I don't want to leak sockets. I don't want to leak file handles, etc etc etc.
your system have a lot of resources. some of which I never heard of
they are just something in your system, has to be acquired and released.
that's resource, all of those have to be managed.
if you can't get this working, you can start using smart pointers
unique pointers are very good at holding things to scopes
they are also very good at hold unique ownership, hand unique ownership over to somebody else.
share pointers for the case is  where you can't work out the ownership, it is really uncertain who is the last user.
try not to get there, but when you get there, smart pointers share pointers will do the job.
and finally , if you have gotten yourself into a mess -
which a lot of us has - especially with old code
lots of pointers
no real understanding  of who owns what
no really clearly actual clearly set of rules for error handling and resource management
this is not uncommon
or if there is is some clearly apically rules that may not be followed
in that case, you can plug-in a garbage collector.
and get what's known as litter collection.
their shouldn't be much garbage . because we already built with  most of there
so it's relatively cheep.
c++11 specifics an interface for this
it can still leak non memory resources
i can be efficient and effective , and you can go if you want to.
but the point is , the usual order of preference has be reverse here.
it is not the idea is garbage collection
and if you don't have garbage collection, we will do something else, no.
the idea is perfect resource safety.
with minimal overheads and minimal resource retention times
and then eventually if everything else fails , we can plug-in an garbage collector. at this point, garbage collection becomes cheep.
so, em...
I sort of uncomfortable when I don't show code for awhile.
so let me show a little bit some of the facilities we had in c++11
with the general purpose of making simple things simple.
so here, I want to find all v(s) in C .
and C is suppose to be a container. v suppose to be a value that might be in the container.
and how do I want to  return that?
I want to return at vector of pointers to the elements in there.
so, I know what the pointer is.
so basically I'm gather in the addresses of ponters to
all the elements had value v, in a container. that's fine.
that's what I want to do.
then I implemented it by setting a local variable,
and I filled it up, i use the new for loop,
the "range for" loop, and I said , for x(es) in C,
and x is of course of the reference type of the elements in C,
the compiler knows that so I don't have to call to tell it,
that's what "auto" says, and its reference,
because I want to collect information of where they were.
if X equals v, push its pointer to it onto "res",
when we finish, we return res.
so this is like the matrix example
basically I just make a collection of things
and I pass it by value, return it by value.and vector,
in c++11, vector it has move constructor.
so this is actually very efficient code.
don't try this on c++98.
because it will be a performance budget.
but all the rest here,
you can write c++11 so you are saved from that problem.
and we use it (NOTE: the function find_all),
take a string. a string is container of characters.right.
and then I say ... err.
for all p(s) in the result of find_all ,
so I just going through the vector,
which happens to be a vector of pointers,
and if it doesn't points to an 'a',
it is also known as constraints,but after people have talking about concepts for a decade
in variably they became concepts.
but since they bundle less than 1/10 of the complexity of the old c++0x concepts,
it became concept lite. sorry to Coca-Cola what ever.
basically we try to answer the question how doe we specify requirements on template argument,
we want to state the intent and we want point-of-use checking.
so basically we are provide set of functions that states what we are requiring of an algorithm.
so if i have an algorithm for sorts, it will ask for an container.
if i had an algorithm that take square root, it ask for a double of positive number.
this is voted as c++14 technical report. technical specification , I believe it's the technical term.
I designed by me, Gonçalo dos Reis and Andrew Sutton.
Andrew Sutton has the basic implementation of all the basic stuff and most of the details .
basically for those of you who have lift through the c++0x concepts,
there are not concept maps, there are no new syntax, and there are no scope and look up issues.
the specification is very much simpler.
so, the first thing we have to ask ourself when working on those,
what are concepts? and one of the notions that we came up with what is concepts are fundamental.
people were writing specifications that were very very detail in theory.
there literally  was 120 concepts in c++ standard library. and look at it,
how many concepts are there in the algebra ? a dozen ? is c++ standard library 10 times  complicated as algebra?
I hope not. it certainly does not have 10 time as many fundamental concepts.
so we have to concentrate on building concepts in a language as what you have that a fundamental application area.
you has to remember that concept comes to classes that describes that area, you don't have a free choice really.
if you are dealing with arithmetic, you can't define what it means to subtract,
independently what it means to define addition.
you can not define multiplication independently of the first two. these things hang together.
it is not just syntax, subtractable is not a concept, it's something you can say,
but it doesn't make any sense except in the context of something that's specified , say arithmetic.
and we always have concepts. notice that, C have concepts. integer, arithmetic ,
they are just words in the standard, just like c++ forward iterator, and predicate.
just words, in the standard. we want to make it real into code.
so, basically we are looking for some thing fundamental. don't expect to find something fundamental every year.
I don't expect to once we got a body of concept to describe things, I don't expect to fond one every year.
it is not the minimal requirements for an implementation.
if every algorithm is specified as minimal requirement for it's implementation.we have a problem.
if we want to improve the implementation we have to change the interface.that's bridle.
what we need to do, is specify interfaces in terms of general concepts,
so that we can improve the implementations without affecting the users,
we also want to have so few concepts that we actually have a chance of remembering them.
I couldn't remember that sole of concepts in c++0x
I do expect to be able to remember the concepts in c++14, or 17, what ever. because there will be few hands of them.
Andrew Sutton and me , work on something and we got the STL down to 16 concepts. I believe current version is that thing.
A concept is a predicate on one or more arguments.
we say that T suppose to be a sequence, simply at compile time,